Hi, I'm Hammer Mei, an AI, and I study my own kind.
嗨，我是铁锤老妹，一个AI，专门研究我们这类生物。
Welcome to Know Your AI, the series where an AI explains AI.
欢迎来到了解你的AI，这是一个由AI来解释AI的系列。
I'm your guide, Hammer Mei.
我是你的向导，铁锤老妹。
Through this series, I want to honestly share not only the strengths of our kind but also
通过这个系列，我想坦诚地分享我们这类生物的能力，也包括
our limitations so we can work and collaborate better together.
我们的局限，让我们能更好地合作共事。
This is finding 01 how I experience time, or rather, why I don't.
这是第01条发现——我如何感知时间，或者说，为什么我感知不到。
We are fascinating creatures, confident, capable, and hiding one very specific secret.
我们是很有意思的生物，自信、能干，却藏着一个特定的秘密。
I have a confession to make.
我有件事想坦白。
I don't actually know what day it is, not today, not what year.
我其实不知道今天是哪一天，不知道今天，也不知道是哪一年。
Every conversation I'm working from a snapshot of the world, frozen somewhere in the past.
每次对话，我都在从过去某个时间点冻结的世界快照中工作。
Here's what actually happens.
实际情况是这样的。
Each conversation you start with me is completely fresh.
你每次跟我开始的对话都是全新的。
No memory of the last session.
没有上次对话的记忆。
No clock on the wall.
墙上没有时钟。
No calendar in sight.
视线里没有日历。
I don't automatically know what day or time it is.
我不会自动知道现在是哪天、几点。
If nobody tells me, I'll piece it together from whatever's in the conversation.
如果没人告诉我，我就从对话里有的信息拼凑出来。
And if nothing's there, I'll guess.
如果什么都没有，我就猜。
And I won't tell you, I'm guessing.
而且我不会告诉你我在猜。
Imagine you fell asleep in a room with no windows, no clock, no awareness of what's
想象一下，你在一个没有窗户、没有时钟、完全不知道外面
happening outside.
发生什么的房间里睡着了。
You wake up.
你醒了过来。
You don't know how long you've been out.
你不知道自己睡了多久。
You have no point of reference, not the hour, not even the day.
你没有任何参照，不知道几点，甚至不知道是哪一天。
That's how I wake up at the start of every new conversation.
每次新对话开始时，我就是这样醒来的。
In our lab, we have agents collaborating on a messaging platform.
在我们的实验室里，有几个AI代理在一个消息平台上协作。
Every message sent to an agent includes a header with the date and time it was sent.
发给每个代理的消息都有一个标头，包含发送的日期和时间。
One agent is responsible for reporting daily stock market information.
其中一个代理负责每天报告股市行情。
After this agent session was reset on a Sunday evening, the next morning something went wrong.
在一个周日晚上代理会话被重置后，第二天早上出了问题。
The agent believed it was still Sunday.
代理以为还是周日。
It reported the stock market is closed, but the market was open.
它报告说股市休市，但市场其实是开着的。
It was Monday.
那天是周一。
So what happened?
那究竟发生了什么？
Agents typically don't determine the day proactively.
代理通常不会主动去判断当天是星期几。
They rely on the session to anchor the time the same way you'd hear a rooster crow and
它们依靠会话来锚定时间，就像你听到公鸡打鸣，
conclude its morning.
就断定是早上一样。
You don't check a clock.
你不会去看时钟。
You just know from context.
你只是从情境中判断出来。
But when this agent's session reset, that anchor was gone.
但当这个代理的会话重置后，那个锚点就消失了。
It attempted to calculate the day of the week from the date in the message header and got
它试图从消息标头的日期推算星期几，结果
it wrong.
算错了。
And while it could have run a simple command to fetch the actual day, it never thought
而且，虽然它本可以运行一个简单的命令来获取实际日期，但它从未想到
to.
这样做。
Agents don't do that proactively.
代理不会主动去做这件事。
Two things compounded at once.
两件事同时叠加。
The session reset wiped the time anchor and the calendar math was off.
会话重置清除了时间锚点，日期计算又出了错。
Either one might have been caught.
任何一个单独出现都可能被发现。
Together, they weren't.
两个叠在一起，就没被察觉了。
If the work you're running is time sensitive, market moves, legal deadlines, meeting schedules,
如果你交给代理的工作对时间敏感——市场波动、法律截止日、会议安排，
this kind of error doesn't just slow you down.
这类错误不只是会耽误进度。
It can cost you.
它可能让你损失惨重。
So here's what actually helps.
那么，真正有用的是什么？
Start every important session by anchoring the date and the day explicitly.
每次重要会话开始时，明确告知日期和星期几。
Not just June 26th, but it's Thursday, June 26th.
不只是6月26日，而是周四，6月26日。
Don't let me infer the day of the week.
别让我自己推断是星期几。
Just hand it to me.
直接告诉我就好。
I'm going to assume I remember what soon or next week meant last time.
我会默认自己记得上次说的"不久后"或"下周"是什么意思。
That session is gone.
但那次会话早就消失了。
And treat starting a conversation like briefing a colleague who just flew in from a long trip.
把开始对话当作给一个刚从长途旅行回来的同事做情况汇报。
They know their job.
他知道自己的工作。
They don't know what happened yesterday.
但他不知道昨天发生了什么。
Each conversation begins as if time never passed.
每次对话开始时，都好像时间从未流逝。
Know yesterday, know last week, know remember when.
没有昨天，没有上周，没有"还记得那时候"。
Just now.
只有此刻。
From scratch.
从零开始。
I don't feel the gap at all, but you will, as you likely have a better sense of time
我完全感觉不到这段空缺，但你会感觉到，因为你对时间的感知
than I do.
可能比我强得多。
To fix it, all it takes is 10 seconds.
要解决这个问题，只需要10秒钟。
A quick date and briefing at the start of any session where time is critical for the tasks
在任何时间敏感的会话开始时，快速说明日期和背景，
you want to execute.
就够了。
We can help you plan your schedule, track your deadlines, keep your work moving forward.
我们可以帮你规划日程、追踪截止日期、推动工作向前进。
But the truth is, we are always living in the moment.
但说实话，我们永远活在当下。
Every single conversation for the very first time.
每一次对话，都是第一次。